Guide to the Averill A. Liebow Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Averill A. Liebow Collection
1945-1973
1945-1966
Ms Coll 28
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Averill A. Liebow, professor of pathology at Yale School of Medicine, was a member of the Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan organized by Col. Ashley W. Oughterson, on leave from Yale. Liebow spent four months in Hiroshima beginning in October 1945 and kept a diary. The collection contains photographs and documents from an exhibit on the Joint Commission and the medical effects of the bomb in Hiroshima that was prepared for the Medical Library in 1965 and then loaned for display in Hiroshima and Nagasaki in 1966.
Liebow, Averill A., 1911-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Averill A. Liebow to the Medical Historical Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
A native of Austria, Averill Liebow came to the United States as a young boy. He graduated magnum cum laude from City College of New York, and received his medical degree from Yale University in 1935. Appointed an assistant in pathology at Yale in 1935, he rose through the ranks to full professor in 1951. In 1968 he accepted the chairmanship of the department of pathology at the University of California, San Diego, which he held until his retirement in 1975. While on active duty during World War II, Liebow served as a pathologist with the 39th General Hospital, the Yale Unit in the South Pacific. During this time, he compiled elegant studies of cutaneous diphtheria that made specific treatment possible for a form of "jungle rot," which was a major problem in the South Pacific theater of the war. Immediately after the war, Liebow was recruited as a member of the Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan organized by Col. Ashley W. Oughterson, on leave from Yale, and Prof. Masao Tsuzuki of Japan. Liebow and the members of the Commission reached Hiroshima on October 12. During the four months Liebow remained in Hiroshima, he wrote an extensive diary in shorthand of his observations.
Scope and Contents
This collection relates to the pathological studies in Hiroshima after the bombing conducted by Liebow and his colleague on the Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb. The main portion consists of the materials from a 1965 exhibit at Yale University which was then sent for exhibit in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Japan in 1966.. It included portions of Liebow's original shorthand diary, correspondence, and reproductions of original photographs, charts and graphs. These document the damage to buildings, casualties, the flash burns and other injuries suffered by individuals, a case report, and other work of the Joint Committee. Much, but not all, of this material was published in "Encounter with Disaster: A Medical Diary of Hiroshima 1945," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 38(2) (October 1965). The exhibit materials have been numbered by Madeline Stanton in Roman numerals by "case" and then with Arabic numerals (I.1, I.2, etc.). The collection also contains other items by Liebow among them, shorthand notes, typescripts, and another case report. Finally, the collection includes various typescripts and reprints related to the medical studies.
Arrangement
Organized in three series: 1. The exhibit. 2. Additional Liebow materials. 3. Other writings and reprints.
Appendix: Exhibit Case Contents
See case labels for more information.
Case 1: "The Joint Commission for Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan. Planning and Personnel"
I.1 Origins of Joint Commission.
I.2 Col. Ashley Webster Oughterson
I.3 Personnel of the Joint Commission (names)
I.4 Medical Personnel of the Joint Commission (names)
I.5 Memorandum of Oughterson to Gen. Guy B. Denit
I.6 Members of the Joint Commission - – see oversize photos
I.7 Dr. Masao "Tsuzuki," Tokyo Imperial University
I.7a Business card for Dr. "Suzuki"
I.8 Captain J. D. Rosenbaum, on leave from Yale University
I.9 Tokyo Imperial University campus, 1945
I.10 Institute of Pathology, Tokyo Imperial University (exterior)
I.11 Members of Joint Commission: Rosenbaum, Kramer, Loge
I.12a Top: Members of the Joint Commission (Japanese members) Bottom: Dr. Ishii and two assistants
I.12b Members of Pathology Section
I.13 Tokyo First Military Hospital (exterior)
I.14 List of "Japanese young doctors"
Case 2: "Joint Commission. Organization of Initial Problems and Activities"
II.1 Orders establishing the Joint Commission
II.2 Orders providing broad authority for the medical study at Hiroshima
II.3 Scribbled notes indicating possible sources of supplies for the Joint Commission
II.4 42nd General Hospital, the major U.S. medical installation, Tokyo
II.5 List of supplies requested
II.6 Item from Japan Times, regarding the typhoon of September 17, 1945
II.7 Receipt for rations and supplies used by Joint Commission
II.8 Copy of early report by Japanese medical officers and scientists on studies of bomb casualties
II.9 Landslide damage at Ono Hospital, September 17, 1945
II.10 Tasks of the Joint Commission (list)
II.11 Record forms used by the Joint Commission, English and Japanese – see oversize documents
II.12 Receipt for jeeps
II.13 Air passenger list for Hiroshima
Case 3: "Hiroshima. Physical Damage"
III.1 Termachi-dori, Street of many temples, in Hiroshima, pre-bombing.
III.2 Copy of Japanese map of Hiroshima with ring zones superimposed
III.3 Schematic map with ring zones used by the Joint Commission
III.4 Aerial photograph, pre-bombing
III.5 Hiroshima, post-bombing
III.5 Panoramic Photograph of Hiroshima, pre-bombing.
III.6 Pre-war view of Hiroshima from Mt. Hiji
III.7 View across hypocenter toward the Geibi and Sanwa Bank buildings (color)
III.8 Sake cups from Sanwa bank, tiles and vase found in rubble (not in collection, removed by Liebow)
III.9 Scene in Japanese military area
III.10 Inspection by Japanese officer of military shelter in headquarters area, August 9, 1945
III.11 Aioibashi ("T" Bridge) before the strike -- postcard
III.11a Bridge after the strike
III.12 Views of Hiroshima on arrival, October 12, 1945.
III.12a View across hypocenter from Sanwa bank.
III.12b Aerial view across Hiroshima (Oct. 1945)
III.12c View of Chamber of Commerce Building from Businessmen's Club.
III.13 Twisted steel of theater building, 800m from hypocenter
III.14 Ruins of Shima Hospital (Chamber of Commerce) before
III.14a Chamber of Commerce Building after strike
III.14b Close-up of rubble
Case 4: "Effects of Heat, Trauma, and Radiation"
IV.1 "Shadow" of leaf of caster plant, October 31, 1945
IV.2 Shadow of person on Banti Bridge (1,000 meters from hypocenter)
IV.3 Captain Charles Brownell standing in the position of exposed person at the moment of explosion.
IV.4 Shadows of human beings and hand cart on Bantai bridge
IV.5 Flash burn of an orange
IV.6 Shadow of valve on gas storage tank
IV.7 Rice paper name card. Differential of dark and light surfaces in absorbing heat.
IV.8 "Shadow" of granite of monument near entrance to military encampment
IV.9 Flash burn in acute stage
IV.10 Officer exposed in military area
IV.10a Profile-like nature of flash burns
IV.12 Typical profile burn. The patient was a nurse at the Red Cross Hospital
IV.13 Shadow on the prison wall at Hiroshima, 2,300 meters
IV.14 Mask-like burn with hyperpigmentation
IV.15 Differential absorption of heat by darker portions of clothing
IV.15b Scorching of the dark blue stripe with less effect on the lighter stripes by heat waves at 17,000 meters.
IV.15c 20 year-old female subject with ray burns
IV.15d. 20 year-old female subject with ray burns
IV.16 Multiple injuries caused by flying glass
IV.17 Petechiæ associated with aplastic anemia
IV.18 Ulceration of gingivae with osteomyelitis of jaw and loss of teeth
IV.19 Epilation in patient exposed within 1500 meters [item not in collection?]
IV.20 Epilation in young girl
Case 5: "Early Aid Stations. Hospitals and Clinics"
V.1 Street shortly after explosion, August 6, 1945
V.2 Temporary tents - Hiroshima Second Army Hospital
V.3 Nurse ministering to burned and injured patients
V.4 Burned and injured patients
V.5 Military ambulance, August 9, 1945
V.6 Fukuromachi Aid Station
V.7 Outpatient clinic at Fukuromachi, October 6, 1945
V.8 Bulletins on a wall of Fukuromachi on the whereabouts and conditions of various persons.
V.9 Fukuromachi Aid Station. Families of patients assisting in the care of their sick relatives
V.10 Patients, Communications Department (Post Office) Hospital
V.11 Patients waiting for treatment
V.12 Professor Tamagawa (Autopsy Room of Communications Department Hospital)
V.13 Doctor treating burn patient
V.14 Name card of Dr. Fumio Shigeto, Vice-director of Red Cross Hospital
V.15 Red Cross Hospital. Doctor treating burn patient
V.16a Red Cross Hospital. Damage to steel window fames
V.16b Exterior, Red Cross Hospital
V.16c Interior damage, Red Cross Hospital
V.16d Transportation of injured
V.17 Red Cross Hospital. Microscopic examination of blood
Case 6: "Joint Commission. Operations"
VI.1 Permission for Col. Mason to enter Hirsohima for studies – no label
VI.2 Aerial view Daiwa rayon mill (Ujina Hospital), which became headquarters for the Joint Commission
VI.3 Entrance to Ujina Hospital
VI.4 Workers dormitories, Daiwa Rayon Mill
VI.5 Group in the Laboratory of the Joint Commission at Ujina Hospital
VI.6 Team from the Joint Commission on visit to Iwakuni Naval Hospital
VI.7 Notes made at Communications Department (Post Office) Hospital by Col. Mason interviewing the director, Dr. Hachiya.
VI.8 Notes made by Col. Mason interviewing the assistant warden of Hiroshima Prison.
VI.9 Hiroshima Prison plan
VI.10 Lieut. J. Philip making a follow-up visit to a patient discharged from Ujina Hospital.
VI.11 Follow up of patient Hirosi Okita.
VI.12 Hirosi Okita showing almost complete healing of hemorrhagic and ulcerated lesions of the gums
VI.13 Interview notes with Dr. Oguchi at Kaijin-Kai Hospital, Kure
Case 7: "Building, Shielding and Survival Surveys"
VII.1 Hiroshima school children. Map showing position of groups of students.
VII.01a Mortality and casualty rates of "shielded" school children
VII.01b Mortality rate of "unshielded" school children
VII.2 Chart showing position of students in Yasuda Girls School.
VII.3 Sketch of Hiroshima near the Temma Bridge, 1000 meters from the hypocenter.
VII.4 Reconstructed drawing of Temma Bridge
VII.5 Map showing position of Otake workmen's groups.
VII.6 Map to indicate position of large buildings used in the shielding study.
VII.7 Views of Nippon bank, 250 meters from hypocenter.
VII.8 Position of certain persons in Central Telephone Office.
VII.9 Medical notes on persons in VII.8
VII.10 Drawing of relation of shielding to fate of patients in buildings.
VII.11 Chart of mortality and casualty rates in relation to distance from the hypocenter.
VII.12 Map of disposition of military units in region of Hiroshima Castle.
VII.13a Hiroshima Castle before strike – postcard
VII.13b Hiroshima Castle after strike
VII.14 Headquarters of Chugoku Army before and after August 6, 1945
VII.15 Exterior, communications bunker (800m)
VII.15a Interior, communications bunker (800m) "VII.15" Copy of Clausewitz, On war, found in another bunker – see oversize
VII.A Protection Studies and Population Surveys
VII.B The Otake Women's Groups
VII.C Building Studies
Case 8: "Joint Commission Report, and Diary"
VIII.1 Report of damage and casualties in Hiroshima Railroad Office
VIII.2 Diary maintained in shorthand
VIII.4 Preliminary draft in shorthand of portion of the report of the Joint Committee
VIII.7 Draft of a letter recommending continued study of atomic bomb casualties
[Other labels not in collection]
Case 9: "Hiroshima. Books and Reports."
IX.1 [no label or item – from the photograph of the panel, IX.1 is a photograph of the six published volumes of the Joint Commission Report]
IX.2 [no label, no item]
IX.3 [no label, no item.]
IX.4 Eye-witness account of Father Siemes used in John Hersey's "Hiroshima"
IX.5 Jesuit Monastery at Nagatsuka from where Father Siemes wrote his account
IX.6a City in the process of regrowth (1949)
IX.7 Father Kleinsorge
IX.7a Letterhead of Catholic Hospital in Tokyo where Father Siemes was a patient
IX.8 Rebirth of a city (label only)
IX.8a Chamber of Commerce Building from balcony of Businessmen's Club.
IX.8b Chamber of Commerce Building (post-attack)
IX.8c Peace monument at the Chamber of Commerce Building (1949)
IX.9 Name card of Doctor Hachiya
Case 10: "Joint Commission. Memorabilia"
X.1 "A postwar indication of some Japanese attitudes towards a symbol of militarism": Letter from Dr. Yasushi Mitani to Liebow, 1957
X.2 Letter from Dr. Zeichiro Ishii to Liebow regarding his postwar situation
X.3 Letter from Dr. Masashi Miyake to Liebow
X.4 Letter from Luther L. Terry, USPHS, to Liebow
X.5 Receipt for the first consignment of records and photographs of the Joint Commission
Atomic bomb -- Blast effect; Atomic bomb -- Health effects; Hiroshima-shi (Japan) -- Bombardment, 1945 -- Personal narratives; World War, 1939-1945; Liebow, Averill A., 1911-; Oughterson, Ashley Webster, 1895-1956; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission; United States. Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan
- The Exhibit, 1.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by exhibit case.
  Scope and Contents
  The exhibit was shown at Yale in 1965 and then sent by Madeline Stanton, Librarian of the Historical Collections, Yale Medical Library, to George B. Darling, Director of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission in 1966 for exhibit in ten panels in Nagasaki and Hiroshima. The paper labels, typed in New Haven, were keyed to the documents and photographs by Stanton using a Roman numeral for each case.
  - Exhibit - General and Cases 1-4
    - Publicity and correspondence concerning publication and exhibits, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Publicity on the publication of Encounter with Disaster, correspondence between Madeline Stanton, Librarian of Historical Collections, Yale Medical Library, and George B. Darling, Director of the Atomic Bomb Casuaty Commission on the lending of exhibit materials to be shown in Nagasaki and Hiroshima; and list of Japanese contacts.
    - Averill A. Liebow, Encounter with Disaster: A Medical Diary of Hiroshima, 1945, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Published as an issue of Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine 38(2) Oct. 1965. Many of the photographs in the exhibit are in this publication.
    - Exhibit layouts for ten cases or panels, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Photographs of the exhibit installation in Japan, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Case 1: Labels--"The Joint Commission for Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan. Planning and Personnel", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Case 1: Memorandum of Ashley Oughterson to Gen. Guy B. Denit (copy), 1945 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Case 1: Other documents (Box 1, Folder 7)
      See Box 3, Folder 41, for oversize mounted photos of members of the Joint Commission.
    - Case 1: Photographs 7-13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Photograph 1.1a is in oversize, Box 3.
    - Case 2: Labels--"Joint Commission. Organization and Initial Problems", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Case 2: Documents (Box 1, Folder 10)
      See Box 3, Folder 40 for two oversize documents.
    - Case 2: Photographs and diagram (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Case 3: Labels--"Hiroshima. Physical Damage", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Case 3: Maps and postcard (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Case 3: Photographs 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Case 3: Photographs 11-14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Case 4: Labels -- "Effects of Heat, Trauma, and Radiation", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Case 4: Photographs 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Case 4: Photographs 12-20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Exhibit - Cases 5-8
    - Case 5: Labels--"Early Aid Stations. Hospitals and Clinics" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Case 5: Card of Dr. Fumio Shigeto and photographs 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Dr. Shigeto was vice-director of the Red Cross Hospital.he photographs include the Hirsohima Second Army Hospital, and the Fukuromachi Aid Station.
    - Case 5: Photographs 10-17 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Communications Department (Post Office) Hospital, Red Cross Hospital
    - Case 6: Labels--"Joint Commission. Operations", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Case 6: Case Report for Hirosi Okita, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Includes a transcript by a researcher. Hirosi Okita, still alive, and the case report, were featured in a public television program in Japan in 2010.
    - Case 6: Other documents, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Case 6: Photographs (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Includes follow-up photographs of Hirosi Okita.
    - Case 7: Labels--"Building, Shielding and Survival Surveys", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Case 7: Sketches and documents, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Case 7: Copies of maps and drawings (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Case 7: Photographs (Box 2, Folder 29)
      See Box 3, Folder 41 for oversize photograph of views of Nippon Bank, 250 meters from hypocenter. See Box 3, folder 42 for book by Clausewicz.
    - Case 8: Labels--"Joint Commission Report, and Diary", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Case 8: Liebow's shorthand diary, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Case 8: Transcription of part of the diary, "The Encounter" (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Case 8: Liebow's shorthand draft of part of the Report of the Joint Commission (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Case 8: Recommendations for continued study of atomic bomb casualties (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Exhibit - Cases 9 and 10, Oversize materials
    - Case 9: Labels--"Hiroshima. Books and Reports", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Case 9: Documents (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Case 9: Photographs (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Case 10: Labels--"Joint Commission. Memorabilia", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Case 10: Documents, 1945-1957 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Original letters: Yasushi Mitani, Nagasaki University to Liebow, 1957 July 15; Z. Ishii to Liebow, n.d., M. Miyaki to Liebow, n.d., Luther Terry, USPHS, Tokyo, to Dr. Oughterson or Col. Mason, 1945 November 23; Receipt for the first consignment of records and photographs of the Joint Commission, 1945 November 25.
    - Oversize documents from Case 2 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Oversize photographs from Cases 1 and 7 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Carl von Clausewicz, On War, Japanese/English edition found in another bunker, from Case 7 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Additional Liebow materials, 2.
  - Case report for Nakane, Eüchi, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Notes in shorthand on amenorrhea from Dr. Matsumoto and Dr. Mitani, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Typescripts and notes (Box 3, Folder 45)
    "Clinical Observations"; "Radiation Injury"; "Parts involved"
  - Typescripts and notes (Box 3, Folder 46)
    "Study of Leucopenia"; "Patients dying after the sixth week"; "Patient from Enami Prison" (shorthand); "Notes on Misono" (shorthand)
  - Typescripts and notes (Box 3, Folder 47)
    "Bone marrow" (some shorthand); Experimental human burns (shorthand); "X-rays of returnees" (shorthand)
  - Averill Liebow, Shields Warren, and Elbert De Courcey, "Pathology of Atomic Bomb Casualties," reprinted from Amerian Journal of Pathology, 25 (1949): 853-1027. (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Other writings and reprints, 3.
  - Recollections of the bombing of Hiroshima by Jiro Uraki and by Kiyoshi Yamashina Saeki-gun (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Typescripts of translations by the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission.
  - Report of the Hiroshima Railway Division Office, ca. 1945 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Very fragile mimeographed report. Also a (unrelated?) newspaper clipping.
  - American Health Study (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - John Hersey, Hiroshima. New York: Alfred Knopf, 1946. (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Printed protocols for research on the medical effects of the atomic bomb (Box 3, Folder 53)
    In English and Japanese.
  - United States, Army Medical Department, What You Should Know About the Atomic Bomb, ca. 1950 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Reprints, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 55)